<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on playing with the black box</title>
    <link>https://hamed.github.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on playing with the black box</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 15:11:49 +0430</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://hamed.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking In Natural Language</title>
      <link>https://hamed.github.io/post/SpeakingInNaturalLanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 15:11:49 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hamed.github.io/post/SpeakingInNaturalLanguage/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;me-and-nlp&#34;&gt;Me and NLP&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time I wanted to learn Natural Language Processing, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the time.
Now that there is a competition on Kaggle &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/c/quora-question-pairs&#34;&gt;Quora Question Pairs&lt;/a&gt;,
I want to seize the opportunity and learn it hands on.
While learning and practicing, I document everything here for others and for my future me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;duplicate-or-no&#34;&gt;Duplicate or no?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to predict if a pair of questions are duplicate or not.
The training set provides 404290 labeled question pairs (1, they are duplicate, 0, they are not duplicate).
We have to predict the probability of being duplicate for any new pair of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-most-naive-solution&#34;&gt;The most naive solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to get lost in the complexity of a model,
so as a benchmark and an starting point,&lt;br /&gt;
I use the simplest model of all
and I guess the probability of duplicates only from the frequency of duplicates in the training set.
The code is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/pinocchio/quora-question-pairs/naive/run/1116931&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its log loss is 0.55411, and it ranks 1727 out of 2168, it exceeds my expectations!
The best solution as of this writing is 0.12684 so I have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Potty training and survival analysis</title>
      <link>https://hamed.github.io/post/potty-training-and-survival-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 11:20:18 +0330</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hamed.github.io/post/potty-training-and-survival-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is time to potty train the Little One (LO).
The objective is to use Reinforcement Learning (RL) so the LO pisses in the toilet instead of his diaper.
The idea of RL is to keep LO on his potty until he accidentally pisses into that.
Then mommy and daddy are ecstatic, jumping up and down with enormous joy,
giving him lots of kisses, stickers and chocolates.
We need to repeat the process over and over again to reinforce the good behavior into the little cute tiny brain of LO.
It is simple but it is not easy.
Survival analysis might come handy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the training, LO pisses on different parts and objects of the house,
from mom’s favorite carpet to dad’s smart phone (False Negatives).
If we want to avoid that,
we have to wait endless hours in the bathroom until the LO gets fed up leaves with no result (False Positives).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the objective is to minimize false positives and false negatives,
spend less time in the toilet, and spend less time cleaning the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let P(t) be the probability of LO pissing during t and t+dt.
This is not a uniform Probability Density Function (PDF).
It depends on many parameters, like room temperature, water consumption and  sweating.
It is even more complicated that that, P(t) depends on the history,
it depends on what happened at before, the last time LO has pissed.
Maybe we can use some survival analysis here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In survival analysis, we are interested in calculation of survival function S(t),
the probability of LO keeping all the urine in his tiny bladder as long as t,
given that he has already pissed at time t=0.
So for example, in our case study we are confident that S(15 min) = 1 and S(4 hour)=0,
for awake subject but for asleep subject, S(t) stays close one for as long as 12 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For awake subject, the half life is about 2 hours,
half of the time he can keep his pajama dry as long as two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a series of observations, we come to this conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First thing in the morning, put LO on his potty. In a couple of minutes, LO will fill both the potty and your cup of joy!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then, you are almost safe during next hour, at the end of first one hour, you give it a shot, then you will try half an hour later and a quarter later and then you leave LO on the potty until he pisses.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good potty training! But be aware that the parameters of your LO might be different from ours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originaly published on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/potty-training-data-scientists-way-hamed-seyed-allaei&#34;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello Hugo!</title>
      <link>https://hamed.github.io/post/hello-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2016 23:34:14 +0330</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hamed.github.io/post/hello-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an on-line dynamic world,
I need an off-line static place of my own to work distraction free,
shut down all the sensory inputs, think, and write about life, science, parenting and technology.
This might be the place.
I am writing this with good old &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vim.org&#34;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; generates the htmls and &lt;a href=&#34;https:/github.com&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; serves the pages, so I always have backups!
Let see if this old fashioned and distraction free method of writing get me back in the mood of writing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My old place was &lt;a href=&#34;https://pnoq.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;blogspot&lt;/a&gt;,
at that time, there were blogs and a google reader to read them all.
Then came facebook, twitter, linkedin and bunch of other things and eventually google reader were downgraded to google plus (too me it was a downgrade.).
They destroyed my creativity and desire to write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to abandon my old blog, twitter, facebook and the rest.
Small things like &amp;ldquo;I went to bathroom&amp;rdquo; will go to twitter,
family and friends related materials will go to facebook but essays and interesting stuffs will be here.
And, there is always &lt;a href=&#34;https://ifttt.com&#34;&gt;IFTTT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>